<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>The Weinberg Foundation</title>
	<atom:link href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/feed/?post_type=post" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org</link>
	<description>Home</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 21:20:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.5.1</generator>
		<item>
		<title>Liquid fission: The best thing since sliced bread?</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/22/liquid-fission-the-best-thing-since-sliced-bread/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/22/liquid-fission-the-best-thing-since-sliced-bread/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 21:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>John Laurie</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3802</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Written by guest blogger John Laurie  What do the two men above have in common? Give up? Well, they both made great contributions to humanity by proposing a change to the established order in which things are done. The man on the left was the first to say “Hey, why don&#8217;t we cut the bread BEFORE we sell it?” The man on the right was the first to say “Hey, why don&#8217;t we have the meltdown BEFORE we put the fuel in the nuclear reactor?” In 1927 Otto Frederick Rohwedder successfully designed a machine that not only sliced the bread but wrapped it. Missouri’s Chillicothe Baking Company installed his first machine, and the first loaf of sliced bread was sold commercially on July 7, 1928. Sales of the machine to other bakeries increased and sliced bread soon became available across the USA. Alvin Weinberg and his team at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) pioneered liquid fission, building and operating the world&#8217;s first nuclear reactors to use a liquid fuel composed of molten fluoride salts. The Molten Salt Reactor Experiment... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/22/liquid-fission-the-best-thing-since-sliced-bread/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><em>Written by guest blogger John Laurie</em><strong> </strong></h2>
<p><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/OttoRohwedder-Historical-Nonfiction-Tumblr.jpg"><img alt="OttoRohwedder Historical-Nonfiction Tumblr" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/OttoRohwedder-Historical-Nonfiction-Tumblr.jpg" width="187" height="254" /></a><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/AlvinWeinberg-ORNL.jpg"><img alt="" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/AlvinWeinberg-ORNL.jpg" width="212" height="254" /></a></p>
<p><strong>What do the two men above have in common?</strong></p>
<p>Give up?</p>
<p>Well, they both made great contributions to humanity by proposing a change to the established order in which things are done.</p>
<p>The man on the left was the first to say “Hey, why don&#8217;t we cut the bread BEFORE we sell it?”</p>
<p>The man on the right was the first to say “Hey, why don&#8217;t we have the meltdown BEFORE we put the fuel in the nuclear reactor?”</p>
<p>In 1927 Otto Frederick Rohwedder successfully designed a machine that not only sliced the bread but wrapped it. Missouri’s Chillicothe Baking Company installed his first machine, and the first loaf of sliced bread was sold commercially on July 7, 1928. Sales of the machine to other bakeries increased and sliced bread soon became available across the USA.</p>
<p>Alvin Weinberg and his team at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) pioneered liquid fission, building and operating the world&#8217;s first nuclear reactors to use a liquid fuel composed of molten fluoride salts.</p>
<p>The Molten Salt Reactor Experiment ran successfully at ORNL from 1965 to 1969. Raw materials were prepared using a meltdown furnace, then allowed to cool before being shipped to the reactor site for re-melting and transfer into the drain tanks of the reactor. The word “meltdown”, which has become synonymous with major accidents in solid fuelled reactors, describes a completely normal and safe process in liquid fission.</p>
<p>The ORNL team proved that this technology could be cheaper, safer, more efficient and generate far less waste than solid fuelled reactors, only to see their funding cancelled and the team disbanded, mainly for political reasons.</p>
<p>But advocates of liquid fission should take heart from the story of sliced bread. Rohwedder originally began working on the bread-slicing machine concept in the 1910s. Unfortunately a fire in 1917 destroyed the factory that was to produce the invention, and the original blueprints. It took him 10 years to recreate his invention.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s been over 40 years since Alvin Weinberg built his liquid fission machine.  Now a new crop of researchers are picking up where he left off. It&#8217;s time for his idea to flow.</p>
<p><em>&#8211;</em></p>
<p><em><strong>John Laurie</strong> is a bilingual engineer who found out about liquid fission last year. He has a web site called <a href="http://energieduthorium.fr/" target="_blank">Energie du Thorium</a> which brings information and news on thorium and molten salt reactors to a French speaking audience.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/22/liquid-fission-the-best-thing-since-sliced-bread/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A simple and &#8220;SMAHTR&#8221; way to build a molten salt reactor, from Canada</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/12/a-simple-and-smahtr-way-to-build-a-molten-salt-reactor-from-canada/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/12/a-simple-and-smahtr-way-to-build-a-molten-salt-reactor-from-canada/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 16:11:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Waste]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3686</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The more I watch developments in the molten salt reactor field, the more impressed I am by the variety of innovative approaches. While every molten salt reactor project I’ve encountered traces its inspiration and probably its basic design to the 1960s Oak Ridge National Laboratory project in Tennessee, the number of modifications that different labs are pursuing is starting to resemble the type of competitive differentiation that defines a free market. Before I get too carried away, let me acknowledge that MSRs are a long way from the market (although with the right breaks, not as long as some would believe). Thus, it’s admittedly premature to compare them to the thriving technological leapfrogging of, say, the automobile or information technology industries. But MSR companies nevertheless are in the early stages of trying to one-up each other as they all chase the general goal of building a reactor that runs on liquid fuel rather than on conventional solid fuel, and that provides a host of improvements in safety, efficiency and long-lived waste reduction. The most recent case in point comes from... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/12/a-simple-and-smahtr-way-to-build-a-molten-salt-reactor-from-canada/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3694" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/OakRidge-MSRE-Welding.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3694" alt="OakRidge MSRE Welding" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/OakRidge-MSRE-Welding.jpg" width="511" height="367" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Welding past, present and future. David LeBlanc will combine features from Oak Ridge&#8217;s 1960s molten     salt reactor with the SmAHTR concept, to make his own &#8220;Integral Molten Salt Reactor.&#8221; That&#8217;s not LeBlanc above. It&#8217;s a welder finishing up the Oak Ridge MSR over 40 years ago.</p></div>
<p>The more I watch developments in the molten salt reactor field, the more impressed I am by the variety of innovative approaches.</p>
<p>While every molten salt reactor project I’ve encountered traces its inspiration and probably its basic design to the 1960s Oak Ridge National Laboratory project in Tennessee, the number of modifications that different labs are pursuing is starting to resemble the type of competitive differentiation that defines a free market.</p>
<p>Before I get too carried away, let me acknowledge that MSRs are a long way from the market (although with the right breaks, not as long as some would believe). Thus, it’s admittedly premature to compare them to the thriving technological leapfrogging of, say, the automobile or information technology industries.</p>
<p>But MSR companies nevertheless are in the early stages of trying to one-up each other as they all chase the general goal of building a reactor that runs on liquid fuel rather than on conventional solid fuel, and that provides a host of improvements in safety, efficiency and long-lived waste reduction.</p>
<p>The most recent case in point comes from the newest of the statups: <a href="http://www.terrestrialenergyinc.com/">Terrestrial Energy Inc.</a>, based in Ottawa Canada, and run by co-founder, president and chief technology officer David LeBlanc.</p>
<p>Dr. LeBlanc is an MSR expert who in January <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/01/18/india-a-hotbed-of-molten-salt-2/">wrote a guest blog here</a> in which he pointed out among other things that it would be in the best interest of the MSR industry to keep designs as simple as possible in order to stand a chance of commercializing within a reasonable time frame.</p>
<p>That advice struck me as sensible, so I made a point of following up with LeBlanc, who incorporated Terrestrial in late 2012 after several years of running an MSR intellectual property company called Ottawa Valley Research Associates.</p>
<p>We spoke by Skype last week, when LeBlanc explained the pragmatic reasoning behind his simplicity push, noting that, “You cannot underestimate the cost of nuclear R&amp;D.”</p>
<p><strong>BURN DON&#8217;T BREED</strong></p>
<p>He outlined his plan for simplicity. In keeping with the theme, let me attempt to keep it simple:  Terrestrial Energy is departing from the original Oak Ridge scheme that called for a two-fluid molten salt reactor that would breed its own fuel.  Instead, Terrestrial’s design calls for a single fluid reactor that would “burn” rather than breed. In the nuclear lexicon, LeBlanc’s reactor is known as a “burner” or a “converter”, not a “breeder.”</p>
<p>While a two-fluid breeder would be the “Ferrari” of MSRs, the world cannot afford to wait for its development, given the desperate need for CO2-free energy sources such as MSRs, notes LeBlanc.</p>
<p>Dual fluid breeder MSRs face a number of extra challenges that will prolong their development beyond that of a single fluid MSR. Among them:</p>
<ul>
<li>The infamous “plumbing problem” that vexed Oak Ridge. In a two-fluid design, one fluid continuously breeds fuel, feeding it into another fluid where the nuclear reaction takes place. The pipes and materials that house and separate the fluids are subject to damaging wear and tear.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Dual fluid breeders require constant removal of fission products, which are the short-lived radioactive waste products of a nuclear reaction (different from the long-lived “actinide” wastes like plutonium) “That requires a lot of R&amp;D and a lot of capital to develop,” notes LeBlanc, who points out that in the 1960s, Oak Ridge had planned to remove fission products on a 10-day cycle by removing a tenth of the salt each day.</li>
</ul>
<p>Ergo, LeBlanc’s single fluid approach, which uses denatured uranium – low enriched uranium that is useless for weapons fabrication.</p>
<p>Compared to a breeder MSR, a burner based on denatured uranium has the obvious disadvantage of not running forever on its bred fuel. LeBlanc downplays that, noting a once-through cycle can last for up to 30 years in a single fluid MSR. In addition, the actinides – which are much less than in conventional reactor waste &#8211; could potentially be removed at that point and recycled into the next fuel batch, minimizing long-term waste storage needs.</p>
<div id="attachment_3699" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/DIAGRAM-IMSRvsModularsvsBeetle2-2.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3699" alt="DIAGRAM IMSRvsModularsvsBeetle2 2" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/DIAGRAM-IMSRvsModularsvsBeetle2-2.jpg" width="511" height="395" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Packing a punch. LeBlanc&#8217;s high power density design means that his IMSR can be smaller than other modular reactors. Above, he compares a 25 MWe and 300 MWe version of the IMSR to the SmAHTR design, and to more conventional modular reactors from Nuscale and Babcock &amp; Wilcox. He borrows from a famous VW ad slogan. Spot the Beetle &#8211; it&#8217;s to scale.</p></div>
<p>Those 30 years, though, would require annual top-ups of uranium. But as LeBlanc points out, the amount would be only about one sixth of the uranium requirements for today’s conventional solid fuel reactors.</p>
<p>Toward the end of its molten salt reactor days, Oak Ridge designed and built a single fluid MSR to run on denatured uranium, along with thorium, called a DMSR.</p>
<p><strong>GET SMAHT</strong></p>
<p>Terrestrial Energy is drawing on that design, but is combining it with principles borrowed from another technology called SmAHTR, for Small Modular Advanced High Temperature Reactor.</p>
<p>The 50-megawatt (electric) SmAHTR is a conceptual innovation at Oak Ridge. It is a small version of the liquid cooled 1500 MWe AHTR  &#8211; on which Oak Ridge is collaborating with China  &#8211; that places the heat exchange inside the reactor vessel.</p>
<p>SmAHTR and AHTR introduce liquid cooling (molten salts) to high temperature next generation solid fuel reactors such as those that use TRISO fuel – pebble bed reactors – and those that use prismatic blocks where the fuel is embedded in graphite blocks that serve as the moderator. Those reactor designs have in the past typically used helium gas as a coolant, which presents various mechanical difficulties and requires high pressure.</p>
<p>LeBlanc believes that by switching the fuel into the molten salt, it offers many benefits of liquid fuel while retaining innovative features of the SmAHTR design. One such benefit: The reactor generates heat directly in the liquid fuel, which permits higher power density operation. Placing the heat exchanger inside the reactor vessel rather than outside – as with some other MSRs – helps.</p>
<p>That, in turn, will allow Terrestrial to build smaller but equally powerful reactors compared to other small modular manufacturers that are using more conventional solid fuel, water-cooled designs, such as <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/12/03/small-step-forward-for-alternative-nuclear-u-s-dept-of-energy-funds-babcock-wilcox-modular-reactor/">Babcock &amp; Wilcox</a> (see diagram above).</p>
<p><strong>NAME THAT REACTOR</strong></p>
<p>Not to be outdone on the nomenclature front, and in keeping with the MSR industry’s nascent differentiation trend, Terrestrial gives its reactor a unique name: the Integral Molten Salt Reactor, or IMSR.</p>
<p>The IMSR will also include patent pending innovations, on which LeBlanc declines to publicly elaborate.</p>
<p>Another IMSR feature: It will use a core of graphite moderator slabs between which the fuel flows which LeBlanc says, “allows other advantages like tricks to limit the amount of neutrons reaching the vessel wall.” This addresses a problem that developers of liquid fuel fast reactors will find difficult to crack, he notes.</p>
<p>With the right combination of power density and core design Terrestrial could build the IMSR with upwards of six times the electrical output of the same size vessel as SmAHTR. It would require replacing the graphite core every four years. The fuel would reside temporarily in a holding tank during the core swap. That marks an improvement over the SmAHTR concept, which requires a swap of the solid fuel core every four years.</p>
<p>LeBlanc envisions IMSR reactor sizes ranging from 25 MWe to 300 MWe.</p>
<p>As with other MSR startups, such as the Japanese single fluid company <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/22/a-plan-to-turn-japans-nuclear-past-into-its-future-with-molten-salt-reactors/">Thorium Tech Solution</a>, LeBlanc is undecided on exactly what salt he’ll use.  While FLiBe salt (lithium fluoride and beryllium fluoride) is commonly associated with dual fluid MSRs, its lithium isotope is problematic, for reasons I’ll examine in a subsequent blog.</p>
<p>LeBlanc says he is considering alternatives including sodium based salts.</p>
<p>In the long run, he has not ruled out a breeder design or thorium fuel, but for now, he’s focused on the single fluid uranium reactor.</p>
<p>“The burner is less challenging than the breeder,” notes LeBlanc. “It greatly reduces technological and regulatory hurdles.”</p>
<p>His goal is to commercialize the Terrestrial reactor by 2021. With his simple and SmAHTR combination, he stands a reasonable chance.</p>
<p><em></em><em>Photo from Oak Ridge National Laboratory. <em>Diagram from David LeBlanc. </em></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/12/a-simple-and-smahtr-way-to-build-a-molten-salt-reactor-from-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>18</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How thorium can solve the nuclear waste problem in conventional reactors</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/05/how-thorium-can-solve-the-nuclear-waste-problem-in-conventional-reactors/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/05/how-thorium-can-solve-the-nuclear-waste-problem-in-conventional-reactors/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 21:24:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Proliferation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Waste]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3623</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Thorium mixed with plutonium and other actinide “waste” could continuously power modified conventional reactors almost forever in a reusable fuel cycle, according to a discovery at the University of Cambridge in England. The discovery, by PhD candidate Ben Lindley working under senior lecturer Geoff Parks, suggests that mixed thorium fuel would outperform mixed uranium fuel, which lasts only for one or two fuel cycles rather than for the “indefinite” duration of the thorium mix. Ideally, the reactors would be “reduced-moderation water” reactors that work on the same solid-fuel, water-cooled principles of conventional reactors but that do not slow down neutrons as much and thus also offer some of the advantages of fast reactors. Lindley’s finding, made while he was a master’s candidate in 2011, bodes well for the use of thorium not only as a safe, efficient and clean power source, but also as one that addresses the vexing problem of what to do with nuclear waste from the 430-some conventional light water reactors that make up almost all of the commercial power reactors operating in the world today and... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/05/how-thorium-can-solve-the-nuclear-waste-problem-in-conventional-reactors/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3632" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><img class="size-full wp-image-3632 " alt="Geoff Parks Horse" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Geoff-Parks-Horse.jpg" width="511" height="342" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Riding the thorium trail. Cambridge senior lecturer Geoff Parks believes actinides could recycle for a long, long time when mixed with thorium in a modified light water reactor.</p></div>
<p>Thorium mixed with plutonium and other actinide “waste” could continuously power modified conventional reactors almost forever in a reusable fuel cycle, according to a discovery at the University of Cambridge in England.</p>
<p>The discovery, by PhD candidate Ben Lindley working under senior lecturer Geoff Parks, suggests that mixed thorium fuel would outperform mixed uranium fuel, which lasts only for one or two fuel cycles rather than for the “indefinite” duration of the thorium mix.</p>
<p>Ideally, the reactors would be “reduced-moderation water” reactors that work on the same solid-fuel, water-cooled principles of conventional reactors but that do not slow down neutrons as much and thus also offer some of the advantages of fast reactors.</p>
<p>Lindley’s finding, made while he was a master’s candidate in 2011, bodes well for the use of thorium not only as a safe, efficient and clean power source, but also as one that addresses the vexing problem of what to do with nuclear waste from the 430-some conventional light water reactors that make up almost all of the commercial power reactors operating in the world today and that run on uranium.</p>
<p>By mixing thorium with “waste” in a solid fuel, the nuclear industry could eliminate the need to bury long-lived plutonium and other actinides.</p>
<p>Lindley’s work surfaced recently in an article about it in the hard copy edition of Cambridge’s quarterly Engineering Department magazine. An <a href="http://www.eng.cam.ac.uk/news/stories/2012/safer_nuclear_future/">earlier version also appears online</a>.</p>
<p><strong>ACCENTUATE THE NEGATIVE</strong></p>
<p>I interviewed Lindley and Parks recently after the magazine story appeared. They explained the crux of Lindley’s discovery: Uranium/plutonium lasts for only a limited period because after one or two cycles, when the actinide portion increases, the mix displays a “positive feedback coefficient.” In the sometimes counter intuitive world of nuclear engineering, a positive feedback is an undesirable occurrence. To use an unscientific term, the reaction goes haywire.</p>
<p>Parks notes that with uranium, “As the amount of actinides in the mixture increases, you get this tipping point where with the uranium mixed with actinide based fuel  &#8211; a key feedback coefficient goes from being negative to being positive, at which point the fuel is not safe to use in the reactor.”</p>
<p>Lindley completes the thought. “The idea is that mixing things with thorium rather than with uranium keeps the feedback coefficient negative,” he says.</p>
<p>In a mixed fuel system, reactor operators would allow a batch of fuel rods to stay in a reactor for about five years, roughly the same as with today’s solid uranium fuel. The fuel would then cool for a few years while the shorter-lived fission products decay, and would then be reprocessed over another year, mixing actinide wastes with more thorium before being put back in a reactor.</p>
<p>And just how long could this cycle continue? “You could just keep doing that forever – until the world runs out of thorium,” notes Parks.</p>
<div id="attachment_3635" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Ben-Lindley.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3635 " alt="Ben Lindley" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Ben-Lindley.jpg" width="511" height="459" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Wasting his future. Cambridge PhD candidate Ben Lindley made the discovery that actinide waste will     burn with thorium for an indefinite period, auguring a way to simultaneously generate power and dispose   of nuclear waste.</p></div>
<p>Lindley’s proposal is the latest possibility to emerge for using thorium reactors to dispose of waste as well as generate power.</p>
<p>As we wrote here recently, <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/22/a-plan-to-turn-japans-nuclear-past-into-its-future-with-molten-salt-reactors/">Japan’s Thorium Technology Solution</a> (TTS) is proposing to mix thorium and plutonium in a liquid molten salt reactor.  Likewise, <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/06/transatomics-msr-uranium-now-thorium-later-investors-in-between/">Transatomic Power</a> in the U.S. has similar plans, although it is starting first with a liquid mixed uranium fuel rather than with thorium.</p>
<p>Lindley and Parks’ idea differs from TTS and Transatomic in one obvious way: It would allow the nuclear industry to carry on building conventional solid fuel, water-cooled designs. That would be strictly true only in the initial implementation of the technology, which Lindley and Parks say would entail thorium mixed only with plutonium rather than also with other actinides like neptunium, americium and curium. That’s because plutonium is now available from sources such as the Sellafield nuclear waste site in Britain. The other actinides are not as readily available, but would become so as it became clear they could be used as part of a mixed thorium fuel, Lindley and Parks believe.</p>
<p><strong>GO EASY ON THE WATER</strong></p>
<p>Once the other actinides enter the mix, the optimal reactor would be a light water reactor modified to have less water and thus less moderation of neutrons in the reaction process. That, in turn, would allow more burn up of actinides.</p>
<p>Lindley envisions a reactor with about a quarter to half the amount of water as in a conventional LWR – enough to serve as a necessary coolant, but little enough so that the water could not slow down neutrons to the extent they do in a conventional reactor.</p>
<p>“It’s not really a fast reactor, and it’s not really a thermal (conventional) reactor,” notes Lindley. “It’s between the two.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.iaea.org/NuclearPower/Downloadable/aris/2013/28.RMWR.pdf">Hitachi, Toshiba, Mitsubishi Heavy Industries and the Japan Atomic Energy Agency</a> all have reduced-moderation water reactor designs (RMWR), according to the International Atomic Energy Agency.</p>
<p>Lindley described them as similar to LWRs but with different fuel assemblies.</p>
<p>The development – and regulatory approval – of RMWRs is one of several challenges facing the deployment of mixed thorium fuel in a water-cooled reactor.</p>
<p>Another is the development and cost of reprocessing techniques for thorium and for actinides other than plutonium (for which reprocessing already exists).</p>
<p>“Splitting thorium from waste or splitting some of the minor actinides from waste has not been done on an industrial scale,” notes Lindley. “There are processes that are envisaged that can do that, that have been tested on a laboratory scale, but never on an industrial scale.”</p>
<p>Another hurdle: Fabricating fuel that as Lindley notes would be “highly radioactive” given the amount of waste that would go into it. “That would have to be done behind a shield,” Lindley says.</p>
<div id="attachment_3638" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Reduced-Moderation-Water-Reactor-JAEA.gif"><img class="size-full wp-image-3638 " alt="Reduced Moderation Water Reactor JAEA" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Reduced-Moderation-Water-Reactor-JAEA.gif" width="511" height="341" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">&#8220;Light water Lite.&#8221; Lindley&#8217;s proposal to mix thorium with plutonium and other actinides would work best in   a reduced-moderation water reactor. The diagram above shows a uranium version of an RMWR, from the Japan Atomic Energy Agency.</p></div>
<p>All of that will require significant research and development funding –more than what Lindley currently has at his disposal, which consists of university research funds and academic scholarships.  One possible source for additional funding could be Cambridge Enterprise, a commercial arm of the university.</p>
<p>U.S. nuclear company Westinghouse has also been collaborating with Lindley on his thorium research. Lindley hopes to test his fuel at the Halden test reactor in Norway, where Westinghouse is a partner in <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/11/01/thorium-poised-for-new-year-coming-out-party/">Thor Energy&#8217;s project to irradiate thorium/plutonium fuel</a>.</p>
<p>It will be interesting to see if any of the <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/13/uk-joins-test-reactor-project-in-france-with-12-5m-commitment/">£15 million that the UK government recently earmarked for nuclear R&amp;D</a> finds it way to Lindley’s project. It’s possible that Sellafield could at least provide plutonium.</p>
<p><strong>FUNDS FROM DECOMMISSIONING?</strong></p>
<p>Given the potential usefulness of thorium as a way of ridding the UK of actinides, it&#8217;s not out of the question that funding could also come from the UK&#8217;s Nuclear Decommissioning Authority, which has a 2013-14 budget of £3.2 billion and which is responsible for managing nuclear waste, including actinides and shorter lived fission products.</p>
<p>As Parks notes, an ultimate goal for applying Lindley&#8217;s discovery “is to come up with a nuclear fuel cycle where the only waste you have to dispose of  is the fission product waste.&#8221;</p>
<p>Parks encourages the government to “grasp the nettle” and financially back the thorium research. He and Lindley note that a multiple-cycle thorium reactor would save money in the long run for among other reasons: uranium prices, although low now, will rise; and a mixed thorium/actinide fuel would eliminate costs associated with nuclear waste storage.</p>
<p>“There are economic benefits in the future to investing in the reprocessing and fuel fabrication aspects now,” says Parks. “And you would completely change what nuclear waste means as far as the public is concerned, in terms of the volume of it and how long it’s radioactive for.”</p>
<p>Lindley and Parks say that their technology could take hold in a commercial RMWR within 10-to-20 years.</p>
<p>For that to happen, they’ll have to find the right mix of collaborators and financial backers.</p>
<p><em>Photos from Geoff Parks and Ben Lindley. <a href="http://www.jaea.go.jp/jaeri/english/ff/news5/gif/03.gif">RMWR diagram from Japan Atomic Energy Agency</a></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/04/05/how-thorium-can-solve-the-nuclear-waste-problem-in-conventional-reactors/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The UK embarks on its alternative nuclear venture, hat in hand</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/29/the-uk-embarks-on-its-alternative-nuclear-venture-hat-in-hand/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/29/the-uk-embarks-on-its-alternative-nuclear-venture-hat-in-hand/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2013 22:38:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3574</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Watching a panel of top British scientists set the UK on the road to new forms of nuclear power this week looked a bit like a scene from an American film where an impoverished farmer puts his son on a bus with a five-dollar bill to start life anew in the big city. There were plenty of wise words from the scientists &#8211; led by the government’s outgoing chief scientific adviser, Sir John Beddington &#8211; who were making public their year-long study and recommendations on nuclear research and development. There was that intriguing mix of promise and uncertainty. As a bonus, there was even action, when over in a separate location government ministers announced they had taken some of the scientific advice to heart and were implementing measures to support new nuclear R&#38;D. But as with the underwhelming fiver handed over by the father, there was an unconvincing amount of money. The centrepiece investment was a £15 million starter kit to encourage industry, academia and government to work together – hardly an amount that will construct, say, a thorium molten... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/29/the-uk-embarks-on-its-alternative-nuclear-venture-hat-in-hand/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3588" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Beddington-RoadmapAnnounce-Halper.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3588" alt="Beddington RoadmapAnnounce Halper" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Beddington-RoadmapAnnounce-Halper.jpg" width="511" height="340" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Chief scientific adviser Sir John Beddington &#8220;cannot see a future&#8221; for UK energy without nuclear, but says that the new nuclear R&amp;D programme will need more funding.</p></div>
<p>Watching a panel of top British scientists set the UK on the road to new forms of nuclear power this week looked a bit like a scene from an American film where an impoverished farmer puts his son on a bus with a five-dollar bill to start life anew in the big city.</p>
<p>There were plenty of wise words from the scientists &#8211; led by the government’s outgoing chief scientific adviser, Sir John Beddington &#8211; who were making public their year-long study and <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168038/bis-13-628-ad-hoc-nuclear-research-and-development-advisory-board.pdf">recommendations on nuclear research and development</a>. There was that intriguing mix of promise and uncertainty.</p>
<p>As a bonus, there was even action, when over in a separate location government ministers announced they had taken some of the scientific advice to heart and were implementing measures to support new nuclear R&amp;D.</p>
<p>But as with the underwhelming fiver handed over by the father, there was an unconvincing amount of money. The centrepiece investment was a £15 million starter kit to encourage industry, academia and government to work together – hardly an amount that will construct, say, a thorium molten salt reactor.</p>
<p>No doubt the vision and early groundwork was there, put forth by the scientists who besides Beddington included &#8211; among others &#8211; David MacKay, the chief scientific adviser to the UK’s Department of Energy and Climate Change (DECC); John Perkins, the chief scientific adviser to the Department for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills (BIS); and Robin Grimes, the chief scientific adviser to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office.</p>
<p><strong>NO FUTURE WITHOUT NUCLEAR </strong></p>
<p>Beddington said at the London gathering that he “cannot see a future” for the UK energy sector without nuclear.</p>
<p>“If it’s going to meet its obligations for greenhouse gas emissions and at the same time have some degree of resilience in the system, there has to be a significant component for nuclear,” noted Beddington, before he revealed the recommendations of a study that goes by various names including “Nuclear R&amp;D Roadmap.”</p>
<p>The roadmap helped shape the simultaneous government announcement led by BIS and joined by DECC of a nuclear “industrial strategy.”</p>
<p>The strategy included £15 million for research at three institutions that will bring together government, academia and industrial interests – key in a deregulated energy environment like the UK, where market forces rather than government runs the energy sector.</p>
<p>It also included the expansion of DECC’s National Nuclear Laboratory (NNL) into a full-fledged central government research and advisory institution.</p>
<div id="attachment_3599" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MacKay-Roadmap-Halper4.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3599" alt="MacKay Roadmap Halper4" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MacKay-Roadmap-Halper4.jpg" width="511" height="346" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">DECC&#8217;s David MacKay says that in the highest nuclear scenario, nuclear could contribute as much as 86 percent of Britain&#8217;s electricity, possibly through a variety of reactor types.</p></div>
<p>NNL is a government owned, commercially operated group that has primarily conducted contract research programs. Its chief science and technology officer Graham Fairhall was part of the 6-person panel that presented the roadmap. NNL’s managing director Paul Howarth was another of the roadmap’s authors, as was Andrew Sherry, the director of the Rolls-Royce-backed Dalton Nuclear Institute at the University of Manchester. Sherry participated on this week’s panel.</p>
<p>(For a full list of the report authors, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168038/bis-13-628-ad-hoc-nuclear-research-and-development-advisory-board.pdf">click here</a> and go to &#8220;Annex B&#8221;).</p>
<p>The scientists urged the development of alternative nuclear technologies if the country is to choose the more nuclear-intensive of the government’s proposed scenarios for cutting British CO2 emissions 80 percent by 2050.</p>
<p>DECC’s MacKay said that in a high nuclear scenario with 75 gigawatts of nuclear capacity, nuclear could provide up to 86 percent of the UK’s electricity, providing 525 terawatt hours (tWh) per year out of a total of 610 tWh, a level he noted is “comparable to France.” Nuclear today provides about 18 percent of the UK’s electricity.</p>
<p>“Clearly I think that if we’re going to be thinking about a significant expansion of nuclear capacity as we move toward our goal in 2050 of an 80 percent reduction in greenhouse gas emissions, we need to keep options open,” Beddington said. “And part of those options is … having the R&amp;D to think about taking it forward.”</p>
<p><strong>NUCLEAR VARIETY SHOW</strong></p>
<p>That “R&amp;D” includes the development of a number of unconventional nuclear reactor types, elaborated MacKay, who noted that, “there are a variety of ways of delivering 75 gigawatts of nuclear.”  Among the alternatives that he and others mentioned: reactors such as “fast” reactors that can burn nuclear waste in a “closed fuel cycle”, molten salt reactors, thorium-fueled reactors, and fusion.</p>
<p>If this sounds familiar, it’s because I broke the story of the then forthcoming roadmap here on the Weinberg blog nearly <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/02/04/uk-government-report-urges-alternative-nuclear-development-including-thorium/">two months ago</a>.  I subsequently tipped it in <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2013/feb/12/report-expansion-experimental-nuclear-plants">The Guardian</a> and on my <a href="http://www.smartplanet.com/blog/bulletin/top-scientists-recommend-alternative-nuclear-for-uk/13346">CBS SmartPlanet</a> blog.</p>
<p>During the course of their year-long study, the Beddington crew gave ongoing advice to the government. That has already resulted in action, as BIS secretary Vince Cable and his DECC counterpart Ed Davey announced the £15 million for coordinated industry, academic and government nuclear research at NNL, Dalton, and at the Culham Centre for Fusion Energy near Oxford.</p>
<p>The government’s BIS-led “industrial strategy” announcement also noted that BIS has provided £18 million to 35 different nuclear R&amp;D projects, including £6 million to OC Robotics, a Bristol, England company that makes a robot controlled laser cutting tool for decommissioning reactors (important for taking down old sites, but not a direct step toward new, alternative reactor technologies).</p>
<p>To further help coordinate industry, academia and government – a theme that the panel repeatedly emphasized &#8211; BIS and DECC announced an alphabet soup of agencies that will work under the government’s recently formed Nuclear Industry Council.</p>
<p>The new Nuclear Innovation Research Advisory Board (NIRAB) carries on the work of Beddington’s ad hoc Nuclear Research and Development Advisory Board, which wrote the advisory report. Another new group, the Nuclear Innovation Research Office (NIRO), will reside at NNL to advance NIRAB’s work.</p>
<div id="attachment_3601" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Perkins-Roadmap-Announce-Halper1.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3601" alt="Perkins Roadmap Announce Halper" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Perkins-Roadmap-Announce-Halper1.jpg" width="511" height="340" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">BIS&#8217; John Perkins hopes for much more industry, academia and government collaboration, including between fission and fusion research.</p></div>
<p>The government stated in its BIS-led announcement that, “It is keen to explore opportunities to back future reactor designs, including the feasibility of launching a small modular reactor (SMR) R&amp;D programme to ensure that the UK is a key partner of any new reactor design for the global market.”</p>
<p>On a related note, the Beddington advisory panel recommended that the UK join SMR development efforts with the U.S. where the Department of Energy (DOE) has a <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/15/u-s-energy-dept-in-2nd-round-of-small-reactor-funding-does-it-have-a-taste-for-molten-salt/">$450 million SMR development</a> programme.</p>
<p>“There’s a potential synergy by working with the Department of Energy in the USA, which is actually setting up a fairly large programme with significant finance in it,” said Beddington.  “In a sense we can work with them, and that is rather attractive. It generates a potential for piggybacking on work that’s going to be done in working closely with the Department of Energy.”</p>
<p>SMRs provide utilities and other end users with lower cost options for adding incremental power, and provide cleaner and lower cost energy in remote areas, where dirty and expensive diesel generators typically serve.</p>
<p>While SMR designs come in conventional uranium-fueled water-cooled varieties, many of the alternative reactors such as molten salt, pebble beds and fast reactors lend themselves to small form factors. In fact various fusion companies are also trying to develop <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/02/15/latest-entrant-in-the-fusion-sweepstakes-lockheed-martin/">small fusion reactors</a>.</p>
<p><strong>FUSION MEETS FISSION</strong></p>
<p>BIS scientific adviser Perkins described fusion “as a long term opportunity, where the UK has a significant position,” given its research at Culham, which participates in the International Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor (ITER) fusion project in Cadarache, France. Perkins pointed out that, “there are crossovers in R&amp;D between fusion research and fission research,” as both involve developing materials that can withstand intensive neutron bombardment.</p>
<p>At the scientific advisers’ press conference, Beddington said it is too early to choose any one SMR technology.</p>
<p>Other recommendations by the scientific advisers included that Britain:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rejoin the international Generation IV International Forum on nuclear development</li>
<li>Participate in EU and other spent fuel recycling research</li>
<li>Invest in “closed fuel” cycles and reactors that don’t require constant replenishing of fuel as conventional reactors do</li>
<li>Work on nuclear development with other countries including key partners France, the U.S., China, India, Japan and South Korea. (Such as with NNL’s recently announced £12.5 million project at the Jules Horowitz test reactor in France)</li>
<li>Invest in nuclear fuel fabrication and infrastructure</li>
<li>Develop exportable nuclear expertise</li>
</ul>
<p>Back to my farmer’s analogy.</p>
<p>That £15 million is a good start. But like junior’s five-spot, it’s barely a token in an industry that the government this week valued at £1 trillion globally.</p>
<p>Serious development of alternative reactors will require serious money. To single out just one example, anyone I’ve ever talked to about building a thorium molten salt reactor sets the ultimate development cost in the billions of dollars. The £15 million pales next to that. So does the £12.5 million that DECC’s NNL two weeks ago said it was investing in the Jules Horowitz test reactor in France, which to be facetious, could buy some pumps and valves and several cases of Chateau Pétrus, but won’t come anywhere near getting the job done.</p>
<div id="attachment_3602" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Grimes-Roadmap-Panel-Halper2.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3602" alt="Grimes Roadmap Panel Halper2" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Grimes-Roadmap-Panel-Halper2.jpg" width="511" height="318" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Foreign Office&#8217;s Robin Grimes expects an additional £10 million next year for irradiation studies.</p></div>
<p>Nonetheless, these are undoubtedly significant developments.</p>
<p>Beddington called this week’s announcement “an important and exciting first step,” that “will reverse the years of decline in taking nuclear R&amp;D seriously.”</p>
<p>And additional government funding appears set for next year, when Grimes anticipates another £10 million for irradiation studies.</p>
<p>At some point, though, those numbers will have to grow by an order of magnitude.</p>
<p>“We probably do need to up the investment in nuclear R&amp;D,” Beddington said. “Unless we get that, I have concerns that there are issues around the nuclear program. But we’ve set out a fairly comprehensive R&amp;D roadmap which I think will have an implication of additional money.”</p>
<p><strong></strong><strong>CHINA ENVY</strong></p>
<p>Given that the UK handed over real control of its energy sector to the market 20-some years ago in Prime Minister Thatcher’s privatization movement, the hope might have to be that the newly strengthened industry-academia-government collaboration instigates more financial interest from industry.</p>
<p>To make up an example: How about if BP invests in SMR development? It’s not so far fetched. <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/06/transatomics-msr-uranium-now-thorium-later-investors-in-between/">Oil giant Shell</a> has shown recent interest in a molten salt reactor.</p>
<p>In what looks like another step to help catalyze industry involvement, BIS – the government’s business department – rather than DECC, ran this week’s nuclear industrial strategy announcement. Prime Minister David Cameron echoed that same business emphasis later in the week when he gave BIS’ business minister Michael Fallon the second job of energy minister within DECC (under secretary Davey), replacing former energy minister John Hayes, who is now an adviser to Cameron.</p>
<p>Fallon should encourage private investment across different energy sectors, including nuclear.</p>
<p>Until industry ponies up large sums for nuclear R&amp;D, the government will continue to suffer from China envy, watching <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/10/29/thorium-offers-energy-independence-to-china-helps-produce-hydrogen-too/">Beijing pour money into nuclear R&amp;D</a>, which it can do because it &#8211; not the market &#8211; controls the energy sector.</p>
<p>Once the real funding arrives in the UK, the ride could lead somewhere. Maybe even on an electric bus powered by nuclear.<b> </b></p>
<p><em>Photos by Mark Halper</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211;</em></p>
<p><em>The government published a number of in-depth documents this week relating to the UK&#8217;s nuclear future: </em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168039/13-631-a-review-of-the-civil-nuclear-r-and-d-landscape-review.pdf"> A Review of the Civil R&amp;D Nuclear Landscape</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168048/bis-13-627-nuclear-industrial-strategy-the-uks-nuclear-future.pdf">The UK&#8217;s Nuclear Future</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168047/bis-13-630-long-term-nuclear-energy-strategy.pdf">Long-term Nuclear Energy Strategy</a> (this is the government&#8217;s industrial strategy announcement)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168043/bis-13-632-nuclear-energy-research-and-development-roadmap-future-pathway.pdf">Nuclear Energy Research and Development Roadmap: Future Pathways</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168038/bis-13-628-ad-hoc-nuclear-research-and-development-advisory-board.pdf">Ad Hoc Nuclear Research and Development Advisory Board</a> (this is the summary set of recommendations from the advisers)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/168044/bis-13-629-nuclear-industrial-vision-statement.pdf">Nuclear Industrial Vision Statement</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/29/the-uk-embarks-on-its-alternative-nuclear-venture-hat-in-hand/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Statement on the UK Government&#8217;s Fission R&amp;D Roadmap</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/26/statement-on-the-uk-governments-fission-rd-roadmap/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/26/statement-on-the-uk-governments-fission-rd-roadmap/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 22:52:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>David Martin</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3562</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Following the release of the UK Government&#8217;s new nuclear R&#38;D &#8216;roadmap&#8217; today, we thought we ought to release a brief statement outlining our views. Incisive blogs from Mark Halper will follow over the next few days. The Weinberg Foundation welcomes the release of the British Government&#8217;s long-awaited Review of nuclear research and development policy. We are pleased that the Government has recognised the need for greatly increased coordination between the UK&#8217;s academic, government and industrial nuclear researchers, and welcome the commitment to fund additional research facilities to support the leadership of the UK academic community. However, whilst the Review does recognise nuclear power&#8217;s essential role in safeguarding our climate and energy security, we believe that the initiatives announced today must be only the first step towards a large-scale revival of the UK&#8217;s nuclear research and industrial base. Many of the Government&#8217;s own Energy Pathway scenarios envisage that nuclear will supply 40-85% of UK electricity by 2050. So, the amount of nuclear power will at least double in the next three decades. The Government&#8217;s proposed funding of fission R&#38;D is not... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/26/statement-on-the-uk-governments-fission-rd-roadmap/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Following the release of the UK Government&#8217;s new nuclear R&amp;D &#8216;roadmap&#8217; today, we thought we ought to release a brief statement outlining our views.</em></p>
<p><em>Incisive blogs from Mark Halper will follow over the next few days. </em></p>
<p>The Weinberg Foundation welcomes the release of the British Government&#8217;s long-awaited <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-business-innovation-skills/series/nuclear-industrial-strategy">Review of nuclear research and development policy</a>. We are pleased that the Government has recognised the need for greatly increased coordination between the UK&#8217;s academic, government and industrial nuclear researchers, and welcome the commitment to fund additional research facilities to support the leadership of the UK academic community.</p>
<p>However, whilst the Review does recognise nuclear power&#8217;s essential role in safeguarding our climate and energy security, we believe that <i>the initiatives announced today must be only the first step towards a large-scale revival of the UK&#8217;s nuclear research and industrial base</i>.</p>
<p>Many of the Government&#8217;s own Energy Pathway scenarios envisage that nuclear will supply 40-85% of UK electricity by 2050. So, the amount of nuclear power will at least double in the next three decades. <i>The Government&#8217;s proposed funding of fission R&amp;D is not commensurate with the scale of the task</i>.</p>
<p>Failure to fund the research and development of at least 50% of the UK&#8217;s future energy supply is short-sighted. &#8220;Market-led&#8221; solutions to nuclear R&amp;D are not enough. It is time for Government to take the lead.</p>
<p>We must make sure the UK utilises the safest, most efficient and most sustainable nuclear technology available. <i>The UK has a unique opportunity to become the world-leader in the development of safer fuels such as thorium and more efficient next-generation reactors like the breakthrough Molten Salt Reactor</i>. The Government must fund the research and development of next-generation nuclear power as a matter of urgency, in cooperation with industry, and with international partners if needed.</p>
<p><i>Lord Hanworth, Treasurer of the All-Party Parliamentary Group on Thorium Energy</i>, said: &#8220;While I welcome Ad Hoc Nuclear Research Board&#8217;s emphasis on the importance of increased nuclear fission research in the UK, it was disappointing that the report did not stress the vital importance of further research into thorium, a cleaner, safer nuclear fuel.  Coupled with advanced reactor designs, such as the molten salt reactor, thorium could bring about a more sustainable era of nuclear power, and make a huge contribution to both our energy security and the fight against climate change.&#8221;</p>
<p><i>For further information please contact David Martin on david.martin[at]the-weinberg-foundation.org.  </i></p>
<p>A PDF of this statement can be downloaded <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Weinberg-Foundation-Short-statement-on-UK-Govt-Review-of-Nuclear-RD.pdf">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/26/statement-on-the-uk-governments-fission-rd-roadmap/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A plan to turn Japan&#8217;s nuclear past into its future with molten salt reactors</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/22/a-plan-to-turn-japans-nuclear-past-into-its-future-with-molten-salt-reactors/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/22/a-plan-to-turn-japans-nuclear-past-into-its-future-with-molten-salt-reactors/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 19:32:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Proliferation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Waste]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3535</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Japan’s fleet of conventional nuclear reactors remains mostly shut following the Fukushima meltdowns two years ago but a significant aspect of it lives on &#8211; its high level nuclear waste. One company has a plan that would use that waste for fuel in an altogether different type of reactor and thus turn Japan’s troubled nuclear past into a revived future. Tokyo-based Thorium Tech Solution (TTS) wants to combine the reactors’ waste – their spent fuel full of actinides like plutonium &#8211; with thorium, the element that many people believe makes a superior alternative nuclear fuel to today’s uranium. And rather than use the fuel in conventional solid rod form, TTS would put it into a liquid, molten salt form. TTS’ molten salt reactor (MSR) would thus deliver the classic advantages of an MSR, while also helping Japan deal with its nuclear waste. Compared to conventional solid fuel uranium reactors MSRs are safer, cannot melt down, generate less long-lived dangerous and weapons-prone waste, and are more efficient. All the better if they use thorium instead uranium, many believe. TTS, founded by... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/22/a-plan-to-turn-japans-nuclear-past-into-its-future-with-molten-salt-reactors/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3527" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Motoyasu-Kinoshita-NRKno.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3527" alt="Motoyasu Kinoshita NRKno" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Motoyasu-Kinoshita-NRKno.jpg" width="511" height="287" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Moto-yasu Kinoshita speaking in Norway in 2011. Kinoshita hopes to run molten salt fuel tests at Norway&#8217;s Halden reactor.</p></div>
<p>Japan’s fleet of conventional nuclear reactors remains mostly shut following the Fukushima meltdowns two years ago but a significant aspect of it lives on &#8211; its high level nuclear waste.</p>
<p>One company has a plan that would use that waste for fuel in an altogether different type of reactor and thus turn Japan’s troubled nuclear past into a revived future.</p>
<p>Tokyo-based Thorium Tech Solution (TTS) wants to combine the reactors’ waste – their spent fuel full of actinides like plutonium &#8211; with thorium, the element that many people believe makes a superior alternative nuclear fuel to today’s uranium.</p>
<p>And rather than use the fuel in conventional solid rod form, TTS would put it into a liquid, molten salt form. TTS’ molten salt reactor (MSR) would thus deliver the classic advantages of an MSR, while also helping Japan deal with its nuclear waste. Compared to conventional solid fuel uranium reactors MSRs are safer, cannot melt down, generate less long-lived dangerous and weapons-prone waste, and are more efficient. All the better if they use thorium instead uranium, many believe.</p>
<p>TTS, founded by the late Dr. Kazuo Furukawa, bases its designs on the work of Dr. Alvin Weinberg, who built a thorium MSR in the 1960s at Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee.</p>
<p>Furukawa started TTS in 2011, soon before his death in December of that year at the age of 84. TTS picked right up where his previous company, ITheMS (International Thorium Energy &amp; Molten Salt Technology Inc.) left off. It aims to build a 160–megawatt electric MSR called a FUJI, and a smaller 7-megawatt model called a miniFUJI (in this case, the word “fuji” implies “the only one” – as in the only solution for a carbon free energy future).</p>
<p>ITheMS, which was run by Japanese politician Keishiro Fukushima with Furukawa as its chief scientist, closed in 2011 after it was unable to secure $300 million it had sought.</p>
<p><strong>MOLTEN IN THE BLOOD</strong></p>
<p>Furukawa, who devoted much of his career to molten salt nuclear research (in the early1980s he worked on an accelerator-drive molten salt system before shifting to the Oak Ridge design), was steeled on making TTS the success that ITheMS was not.</p>
<p>His successors at TTS are working hard to realize that. In a stroke of abject determination, his younger brother Masaaki Furukawa, who is the company’s president, has declared that TTS will build a working prototype by 2018 &#8211; not one near the scale of even a miniFUJI, but a tiny primitive version that will produce electricity and prove the concept.</p>
<p>Masaaki Furukawa’s fellow shareholders at TTS include Kazuo Furukawa’s son Kazuro, who is a professor at the Koh Energy Kasokuki higher energy accelerator research group; and chief engineer Moto-yasu Kinoshita.</p>
<p>Kinoshita is also a vice president of the International Thorium Molten Salt Forum and a researcher at the University of Tokyo. We <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/11/05/alvin-weinberg-good-ideas-in-any-language/">featured him on the Weinberg blog last November</a> from Shanghai, where he was proudly displaying a Chinese language version of Alvin Weinberg&#8217;s autobiography, <em>The First Nuclear Era – The Life and Times of a Technological Fixer.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_3542" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Motoyasu-Kinoshita-Weinberg-Book-Halper.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3542" alt="Motoyasu Kinoshita Weinberg Book Halper" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Motoyasu-Kinoshita-Weinberg-Book-Halper.jpg" width="511" height="340" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The source. Kinoshita displays a Chinese language version of Alvin Weinberg&#8217;s autobiography at the       Thorium Energy Conference in Shanghai last November. Weinberg&#8217;s MSR design has inspired TTS and other new MSR companies.</p></div>
<p>I spoke with him  at length this week via Skype, when Kinoshita told me that TTS could begin building commercial FUJIs and miniFUJIs by around 2025.</p>
<p>Obviously, a lot has to happen between now and then, not the least of which will be that TTS has to secure funding.</p>
<p>The company is taking things in stages.</p>
<p>The focus at the moment will require that TTS raise a mere $300,000 – pocket change in the world of nuclear development &#8211; to soon test different molten salts. TTS wants to establish which it will use, as it tries to develop a fluid that will not corrode common nickel alloys such as hastelloy and inconel that would form the plumbing in an MSR.</p>
<p>While some competing MSR researchers want to substitute and develop exotic metal replacements, Kinoshita says that TTS is determined to stick with existing materials, an approach he calls “practical and cheaper.”</p>
<p><strong>SEARCHING FOR CHEMISTRY</strong></p>
<p>Instead of material moves, Kinoshita says TTS will apply “chemistry control” to come up with the right recipe of molten salt ingredients that would avoid corroding common alloys.</p>
<p>A typical fluid in MSR designs is a compound known as FLiBe, which is a mixture of lithium fluoride and beryllium fluoride. Kinoshita notes that it is the fluid that Oak Ridge National Laboratory used in the MSR it built in the 1960s under the direction of Weinberg (from whom the Weinberg Foundation, publisher of this blog, takes its name; “FLiBe” is also the namesake of Huntsville, Ala.-based MSR company Flibe Energy, another Oak Ridge inspired group).</p>
<p>In fact, Oak Ridge included beryllium to help avoid corrosion.</p>
<p>But Kinoshita notes that beryllium has its own problems.</p>
<p>“It is not easy to use beryllium – it’s a controlled material because of its toxicity,” he says.</p>
<p>And perhaps more to the point in TTS’ plans – beryllium does not get along well with plutonium, which is one of the “waste” elements that would help form TTS’ mixed thorium fuel.</p>
<p>So TTS is investigating other solutions, such as adding sodium to FLiBe. It is also considering another molten salt called FLiNaK, which is a combination of sodium, potassium and lithium.</p>
<p>Kinoshita is confident that TTS will be able to raise the $300,000, which he thinks could come from anti-nuclear weapon groups who would back the idea of destroying weapons-linked nuclear waste.</p>
<p><strong>THE NEXT TEST</strong></p>
<p>TTS could wrap up its molten salt tests by “this year or next,” Kinoshita says.</p>
<p>It could then focus on a bigger project, would require about $5 million: Testing the behaviour of nuclear waste’s transuranic elements like neptunium, plutonium, americium and curium.</p>
<p>For that, TTS plans to burn simulated-fuel versions of molten salts in a test reactor. It hopes to use the Halden reactor in Norway – the same place where Norway’s Thor Energy will soon begin irradiating a thorium-plutonium mix, with backing from Westinghouse and others.</p>
<p>Other possible test sites would be the Nuclear Research Institute in the Czech Republic, and Japan’s currently halted Japan Materials Testing Reactor.</p>
<p>Kinoshita envisions about five years of the transuranic tests. Then begins the heavy lifting of building the MSR and overcoming technical challenges that all MSR developers face.</p>
<p><strong>FREEZING HOT</strong></p>
<p>Among the hurdles: molten salts in MSRs tend to solidify when temperature drop to around 460 degrees C.  Molten salt reactors are meant to operate at somewhere between 700 degrees C and 900 degrees C. That’s much higher than conventional reactors, and is a reason why MSRs can make more efficient use of fuel (higher temperatures burn more fuel). One of the great attributes of molten salts is that they don’t boil easily – thus they can flow as they need to in an MSR system at high temperatures.</p>
<p>But if things cool too much, they solidify, and pipes can burst. So-called “freezing accidents” would not pose meltdown type threats associated with extreme accidents in conventional reactors, but they would destroy the reactor.</p>
<p>Another challenge: TTS will have to develop chemistry to separate waste from fuel within its reactor. TTS is using a single fluid approach, unlike the dual fluid approach under development at other MSR projects. In a dual fluid MSR, one fluid produces fissile uranium 233 fuel from fertile thorium, and feeds that into a second fluid where reactions take place. TTS’ single fluid technology will have to apply a still unproven technique for separating the fissile uranium 233 from the fertile thorium and from wastes.</p>
<p>On the other hand, companies developing the two fluid approach will have to overcome materials challenges – in a typical MSR design, the silicon carbide that separates the two molten salt fluids can fail (which is why Furukawa decided on the single fluid approach in the first place).</p>
<p>All told, Kinoshita thinks TTS can start building commercial miniFUJIs and FUJIs by around 2025.</p>
<p>As for the 2018 proof of concept model? That will be tough, but not impossible. Scientific geniuses are welcomed to apply at TTS.</p>
<p><em>Photos: Kinoshita in Norway, <a href="http://www.nrk.no/nyheter/distrikt/nrk_trondelag/1.7554421">Aksel Kroglund Persson/NRK</a>. Kinoshita with Weinberg book, Mark Halper</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/22/a-plan-to-turn-japans-nuclear-past-into-its-future-with-molten-salt-reactors/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Emerging markets will help power 30 percent growth in nuclear by 2020</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/18/emerging-markets-will-help-power-30-percent-growth-in-nuclear-by-2020/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/18/emerging-markets-will-help-power-30-percent-growth-in-nuclear-by-2020/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 20:17:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Waste]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3486</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Is the nuclear renaissance back on? A new report from London-based business intelligence firm GlobalData would suggest it is, triggered in large measure by a demand for power from emerging markets and from some 45 countries that have yet to deploy it. &#8220;Global nuclear energy generation will climb by almost 30% by the end of the decade, thanks in part to an influx of new nations developing nuclear programs,&#8221; GlobalData says in a press release. It forecasts that 198 new reactors will begin commercial operations by 2020, by which time worldwide nuclear generation will jump to 3.1 million GWh, up from 2.4 million GWh in 2012. &#8220;At present there are around 45 nuclear-free countries looking at adding the controversial power source to their energy portfolio, including the UAE, Turkey, Poland and Bangladesh,&#8221; GlobalData notes. China, India and South Korea will lead the surge, as nuclear generation in the Asia Pacific region will jump from 324,000 GWh last year to 852,000 GWh by 2020, GlobalData says. ASIAN ACTIVITY In China alone,the World Nuclear Association (WNA) has identified 79 nuclear reactors either... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/18/emerging-markets-will-help-power-30-percent-growth-in-nuclear-by-2020/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3507" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 500px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Bangladesh-Map-GreenwichMeantime2.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3507" alt="Bangladesh Map GreenwichMeantime" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Bangladesh-Map-GreenwichMeantime2.jpg" width="490" height="382" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Newcomers like Bangladesh will help drive a nuclear revival, says GlobalData.</p></div>
<p>Is the nuclear renaissance back on?</p>
<p>A new report from London-based business intelligence firm GlobalData would suggest it is, triggered in large measure by a demand for power from emerging markets and from some 45 countries that have yet to deploy it.</p>
<p>&#8220;Global nuclear energy generation will climb by almost 30% by the end of the decade, thanks in part to an influx of new nations developing nuclear programs,&#8221; <a href="http://www.globaldata.com/PressReleaseDetails.aspx?PRID=698&amp;Type=Industry&amp;Title=Nuclear+Energy">GlobalData says in a press release</a>.</p>
<p>It forecasts that 198 new reactors will begin commercial operations by 2020, by which time worldwide nuclear generation will jump to 3.1 million GWh, up from 2.4 million GWh in 2012.</p>
<p>&#8220;At present there are around 45 nuclear-free countries looking at adding the controversial power source to their energy portfolio, including the UAE, Turkey, Poland and Bangladesh,&#8221; GlobalData notes.</p>
<p>China, India and South Korea will lead the surge, as nuclear generation in the Asia Pacific region will jump from 324,000 GWh last year to 852,000 GWh by 2020, GlobalData says.</p>
<p><strong>ASIAN ACTIVITY</strong></p>
<p>In China alone,the World Nuclear Association (WNA) has identified 79 nuclear reactors either under construction or planned, and another 86 proposed, for a total of about 165 reactors. WNA&#8217;s <a href="http://www.wnfc.info/programme.html">World Nuclear Fuel Cycle 2013</a> conference in Singapore next month will include presentations from Asian countries not generally known as nuclear energy centers, such as Bangladesh and Vietnam.</p>
<p>Growth in those nations contrasts sharply with some Western countries like Germany, which decided to abandon nuclear power after the meltdowns at Japan&#8217;s Fukushima Daiichi reactors following the tragic tsunami and earthquake two years ago.</p>
<p><strong>RENAISSANCE RESUMED</strong></p>
<p>A 30 percent expansion indicates that the nuclear renaissance which was building prior to Fukushima is returning.</p>
<p>The reasons for a nuclear revival are just as compelling now as they were pre-Fukushima: Nuclear provides a low carbon energy to help combat climate change, is not subject to price volatility the way fossil fuels are, and offers a steady supply of baseload power, unlike intermittent renewables like wind and solar.</p>
<p>Such mounting interest should help underpin research, development and ultimately, deployment of alternative forms of nuclear power that can improve on the safety, efficiency and waste of conventional reactors. These would include thorium fuel, as well as reactors built on molten salt, pebble bed, &#8220;fast&#8221; and fusion designs, among others.</p>
<p><em>Map from greenwichmeantime.com</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/18/emerging-markets-will-help-power-30-percent-growth-in-nuclear-by-2020/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. Energy Dept. in 2nd round of small reactor funding. Does it have a taste for molten salt?</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/15/u-s-energy-dept-in-2nd-round-of-small-reactor-funding-does-it-have-a-taste-for-molten-salt/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/15/u-s-energy-dept-in-2nd-round-of-small-reactor-funding-does-it-have-a-taste-for-molten-salt/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2013 22:41:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Waste]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3432</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[You might have missed the quiet announcement earlier this week: The U.S. Department of Energy has opened a second round in its $450 million program to fund small modular nuclear reactors, following its grant to Babcock &#38; Wilcox late last year. In a logical scenario, the next recipient would receive about $227 million, or roughly the same as what B&#38;W is believed to have won. &#8220;The Energy Department will solicit proposals for cost-shared small modular reactor projects that have the potential to be licensed by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and achieve commercial operation around 2025,&#8221; DOE said in a press release. Small modular reactors (SMRs) are much smaller than the gigawatt-plus size of new conventional designs. DOE said it is &#8220;seeking 300 megawatts or smaller.&#8221; They auger lower costs because they can be manufactured in more of an assembly-line manner and transported complete to a site, and because they would allow utilities and other end users to add power in increments. They also lend themselves to installation in remote areas where they could provide a less expensive alternative to diesel... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/15/u-s-energy-dept-in-2nd-round-of-small-reactor-funding-does-it-have-a-taste-for-molten-salt/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3455" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Chu-Obama-Charles-Watkins-Wiki.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3455 " alt="Chu Obama Charles Watkins Wiki" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Chu-Obama-Charles-Watkins-Wiki.jpg" width="511" height="365" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">&#8220;Before I go Mr. President, let me tell you about these molten salt reactors.&#8221; That&#8217;s a completely made-up conversation. But outgoing U.S. Energy Secretary Steven Chu (l), this week did say that small modular reactors will be key to the country&#8217;s low carbon energy future. MSRs are one variety of them.</p></div>
<p>You might have missed the quiet announcement earlier this week: The U.S. Department of Energy has opened a second round in its $450 million program to fund small modular nuclear reactors, following its grant to Babcock &amp; Wilcox late last year.</p>
<p>In a logical scenario, the next recipient would receive about $227 million, or roughly the same as what B&amp;W is believed to have won.</p>
<p>&#8220;The Energy Department will solicit proposals for cost-shared small modular reactor projects that have the potential to be licensed by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and achieve commercial operation around 2025,&#8221; <a href="http://energy.gov/articles/energy-department-announces-new-funding-opportunity-innovative-small-modular-reactors">DOE said in a press release</a>.</p>
<p>Small modular reactors (SMRs) are much smaller than the gigawatt-plus size of new conventional designs. DOE said it is &#8220;seeking 300 megawatts or smaller.&#8221;</p>
<p>They auger lower costs because they can be manufactured in more of an assembly-line manner and transported complete to a site, and because they would allow utilities and other end users to add power in increments. They also lend themselves to installation in remote areas where they could provide a less expensive alternative to diesel generators.</p>
<p><strong>CLEAN MACHINES</strong></p>
<p>Another advantage: they can potentially serve as sources of clean heat for industrial processes in factories and oil fields.</p>
<p>Outgoing Energy Secretary Steven Chu made it clear that they are an important part of a low carbon energy future.</p>
<p>“As President Obama said in the State of the Union, the Administration is committed to speeding the transition to more sustainable sources of energy,&#8221; Chu said in the release. &#8220;Innovative energy technologies, including small modular reactors, will help provide low-carbon energy to American homes and businesses, while giving our nation a key competitive edge in the global clean energy race.&#8221;</p>
<p>The DOE release also says that SMRs will offer &#8220;innovative and effective solutions for enhanced safety, operations and performance.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>SMALL, MODULAR AND SALTY</strong></p>
<p>With all that in mind, it seems to me that DOE should take a serious look at molten salt reactors (MSRs) and pebble bed reactors (PBRs), rather than only look at shrunken versions of conventional uranium fueled, water-cooled reactor, such as what B&amp;W is building with its 180-megawatt mPower reactor (utility Tennessee Valley Authority plans to deploy two mPower units by 2021).</p>
<p>&#8220;Conventional&#8221; SMR companies like Nuscale Power, Gen4 Energy  and Westinghouse could well vie for the next round with small water-cooled reactors. But is this not also a funding opportunity for MSR companies like <a href="http://flibe-energy.com/">Huntsville, Ala.&#8217;s Flibe Energy</a> and <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/06/transatomics-msr-uranium-now-thorium-later-investors-in-between/">Cambridge, Mass.-based Transatomic Power</a>?</p>
<p>Most MSR designs tick the &#8220;smaller&#8221; box, and would certainly qualify in the &#8220;enhanced safety, operations and performance&#8221; category. They are meltdown proof, operate at normal atmospheric pressure rather than at the high pressure of  many water-cooled designs, and they make more efficient use of fuel because they operate at higher temperatures. They also leave less waste, and in certain designs, can use nuclear wast as fuel. DOE&#8217;s 2025 target would be feasible.</p>
<p>Transatomic might be counted out if it sticks firmly to its intention to build <a href="http://transatomicpower.com/products.php">a 500-megawatt reactor</a>, which is above the 300 megawatt ceiling stated by DOE. But it seems that at their early stage of development, Transatomic could tinker with size.</p>
<p>Flibe fits right into the modular size, as it&#8217;s targeting between 10 and 50 megawatts, and up to 250 megawatts.</p>
<p><strong>DON&#8217;T FORGET THE PEBBLES</strong></p>
<p>And don&#8217;t rule out a pebble bed option, either. Like MSRs, gas-cooled PBRs run at high temperatures. They fit well into small, modular form factors. <a href="http://www.smartplanet.com/blog/intelligent-energy/westinghouse-enters-us-china-nuclear-collaboration/17252">A DOE-China collaboration</a> ties the two ideas together, as it is looking into using molten salt coolants in solid fuel high temperature reactor (MSRs uses molten salts as part of their liquid fuel mix, as well as for the coolants that aborb the heat of a nuclear reaction and transfer it to a turbine).</p>
<p>In fact conventional giant Westinghouse is the commercial adviser to the DOE-China project, so it could have an interest in applying for funding for an alternative design, although it is almost certainly much further along with its small conventional reactor.</p>
<p>There is plenty of cross-pollinated interest among the various alternative parties that together could build a case for funding alternative nuclear. Westinghouse  - the commercial adviser to the U.S.-China molten salt coolant project &#8211; ran the <em>Advanced Reactors </em>track at last November&#8217;s <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/11/09/thorium-knocks-on-the-door-at-san-diegos-american-nuclear-society-confab/">American Nuclear Society&#8217;s annual winter conference</a> (ANS) in San Diego, where the presentations included molten salts and high temperature reactors.</p>
<p>They also included talks by University of California Berkeley nuclear engineering head Per Peterson (he chaired the 5-day conference as well), who is known for his  interest in pebble bed reactors and in molten salt coolants. Peterson is also on the board of advisors at MSR company Flibe. In fact Peterson chaired the 5-day conference. Massachusetts Institute of Technology research scientist Charles Forsberg, a member of the DOE-China team, also presented in the alternative nuclear track.</p>
<p>Another MIT expert, Richard Lester, is a key adviser to MSR company Transatomic. Lester is the head of the department of nuclear science and engineering at MIT, where he is also the “Japan Steel Industry Professor&#8221; (I conjure up images of molten salt reactors supplying heat to steel mills when I see that).</p>
<p><b>A MORE NUCLEAR DOE?</b></p>
<p>And MIT, of course, is home to President Obama&#8217;s nominee for Chu&#8217;s replacement as Energy Secretary, <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/08/good-week-for-nuclear-environmental-economic-backing-from-japan-bill-gates-mit-and-obama/">the pro-nuclear physicist Ernest Moniz</a>.</p>
<p>These individuals are not all united behind all the same causes and companies, but most of them share a big vested interest in alternative nuclear. It seems as though together, they could raise government interest &#8211; and backing &#8211; in the area.</p>
<p>Of course they&#8217;ll have to find funding elsewhere as well. I could imagine an oil company getting behind the development of a small MSR, for among other reasons, to use as a heat source. Or space agency NASA. The military might also want to invest &#8211; an MSR could help domestic bases disconnect from the creaky public grid, as Flibe president Kirk Sorensen has pointed out.</p>
<p>How about venture capital? Maybe. Flibe has added Bram Cohen to its board of advisers. Cohen is the founder of Internet company BitTorrent, where he has experience at raising $40 million in venture capital. Transatomic is getting ready to attempt a &#8220;Series A&#8221; round of venture financing.</p>
<p>Those possibilities could make a good mix. A DOE award should be a possibility. In the current round it might be a long shot. But so was the moon.</p>
<p><em>Photo from Charles Watkins, White House photographer, via Wikimeda</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/15/u-s-energy-dept-in-2nd-round-of-small-reactor-funding-does-it-have-a-taste-for-molten-salt/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>UK joins test reactor project in France with £12.5m commitment</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/13/uk-joins-test-reactor-project-in-france-with-12-5m-commitment/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/13/uk-joins-test-reactor-project-in-france-with-12-5m-commitment/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 22:16:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3403</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The research and development of alternative nuclear technologies received a boost yesterday when the UK committed £12. 5 million ($18.6 million) to join a group of nine other governments and three utilities in a French test reactor. The Jules Horowitz Reactor (JHR), under construction in Cadarache, France (the same southern city where the ITER fusion tokamak is rising) is scheduled for completion by 2016, at a cost of €750 million ($972 million). The JHR website says that the reactor will support the development of  &#8221;different power reactor systems&#8221; including those based on &#8220;existing and future technologies.&#8221; &#8220;It will have the potential to look at thorium fuels, fast reactors, novel fuel designs for SMRs (small modular reactors), etc.,&#8221; explained Adrian Bull, director of external relations at the UK&#8217;s National Nuclear Laboratory (NNL) in an email exchange. NNL is the Sellafield, England-based privately run research lab owned by the UK&#8217;s Department of Energy and Climate Change. It is leading the UK&#8217;s involvement at JHR, where it joins government research groups from France, the Czech Republic, Japan, Spain, Belgium, India, Finland and Israel who... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/13/uk-joins-test-reactor-project-in-france-with-12-5m-commitment/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3415" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 521px"><a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Davey-EmieFrenchAmbassador.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-3415" alt="Davey EmieFrenchAmbassador" src="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Davey-EmieFrenchAmbassador.jpg" width="511" height="298" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Splitsville. UK Energy Secretary Ed Davey (r) and French Ambassador Bernard Emié at the London       signing of Britain&#8217;s £12.5 million commitment to the Jules Horowitz test reactor in France, where the two countries and others will test new techniques and materials for splitting atoms.</p></div>
<p>The research and development of alternative nuclear technologies received a boost yesterday when the UK committed £12. 5 million ($18.6 million) to join a group of nine other governments and three utilities in a French test reactor.</p>
<p>The Jules Horowitz Reactor (JHR), under construction in Cadarache, France (the same southern city where the ITER fusion tokamak is rising) is <a href="http://www.cad.cea.fr/rjh/jhr-cadarache.html">scheduled for completion by 2016</a>, at a cost of €750 million ($972 million). The JHR website says that the reactor will <a href="http://www.cad.cea.fr/rjh/faq.html">support the development of  &#8221;different power reactor systems&#8221;</a> including those based on &#8220;existing and future technologies.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;It will have the potential to look at thorium fuels, fast reactors, novel fuel designs for SMRs (small modular reactors), etc.,&#8221; explained Adrian Bull, director of external relations at the UK&#8217;s National Nuclear Laboratory (NNL) in an email exchange.</p>
<p>NNL is the Sellafield, England-based privately run research lab owned by the UK&#8217;s Department of Energy and Climate Change. It is leading the UK&#8217;s involvement at JHR, where it <a href="http://www.cad.cea.fr/rjh/index.html">joins government research groups</a> from France, the Czech Republic, Japan, Spain, Belgium, India, Finland and Israel who were already active there.</p>
<p>The project also includes the European Commission, as well nuclear company Areva, French utility EDF, and Swedish utility Vattenfall.</p>
<p><strong>GAINING ACCESS</strong></p>
<p>“It’s vital that we cooperate on issues like safety and R&amp;D,&#8221; said John Hayes, Minister of State for Energy at DECC, in a press release. &#8220;We are putting our money where our mouth is by confirming our contribution of £12.5m to the Jules Horowitz research reactor in France and guaranteeing the UK access rights to the project.”</p>
<p>NNL managing director Paul Howarth said the commitment to the JHR &#8220;is an important step towards returning the UK to the international &#8216;top table&#8217; in the arena of civil nuclear R&amp;D.&#8221;</p>
<p>The JHR will also supply hospitals with medical isotopes.</p>
<p>It is part of a fleet of six <a href="http://www.emtr.eu/welcome.html">European Union &#8220;material test reactors&#8221;</a> including the Halden Reactor in Norway, which <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/11/01/thorium-poised-for-new-year-coming-out-party/">will soon begin irradiating thorium fue</a>l here, and which <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2012/11/28/nuclear-reactors-for-industrial-heat-not-just-good-on-paper-norways-doing-it/">supplies heat to a nearby paper mill</a></p>
<p>JHR will replace the older Osiris Reactor, also in France. At 100 megawatts, it will be the largest of the European test reactors.  France&#8217;s Alternative Energies and Atomic Energy Commission (CEA), a major backer at JHR, has also been involved in the others.</p>
<p><strong>EUROPE&#8217;S NUCLEAR DOZEN</strong></p>
<p>Also yesterday, the UK and 11 other EU nations in London announced a <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/140109/final_EU_Nuclear_Energy_Communiqu_.pdf">&#8220;Joint Ministerial Communique on Nuclear Energy in Europe&#8221;</a> affirming collaboration on making nuclear &#8220;a part in the EU&#8217;s future low carbon energy mix.&#8221;</p>
<p>“It’s vital for our economy that we work with our European partners to make the EU a leading destination for investment in new low-carbon energy infrastructure,&#8221; said Ed Davey, the UK&#8217;s energy secretary (Hendry&#8217;s boss). “This communiqué signals a move to a stronger, better and closer working relationship between Member States on nuclear energy. By working together to enable low carbon energy projects to come forward we will go some way to reducing the EU’s carbon emissions and ensuring greater energy security.&#8221;</p>
<p>The 12 countries will hold their next ministerial meeting in the Czech Republic, a country where nuclear research includes a thorium-fueled molten salt reactor.</p>
<p>The 12 are the UK, France, the Czech Republic, Spain, Holland, Finland, Poland, Hungary, Slovakia, Bulgaria, Romania and Lithuania.</p>
<p><em>Photo from UK Department of Energy and Climate Change, via Flickr</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/13/uk-joins-test-reactor-project-in-france-with-12-5m-commitment/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bill Gates&#8217; excellent case for new types of nuclear power</title>
		<link>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/11/bill-gates-excellent-case-for-new-types-of-nuclear-power/</link>
		<comments>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/11/bill-gates-excellent-case-for-new-types-of-nuclear-power/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 21:04:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Mark Halper</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Safety]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Waste]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/?p=3313</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8220;Nuclear innovation stopped in the 1970s.&#8221; &#160; Bill Gates has been making nuclear headlines over the last few days after the told a gathering of international energy executives near Denver that solar and wind technologies won&#8217;t cut it as a source of baseload power, and that the U.S. government should fund nuclear research and development. His remarks were reported by Reuters and have been widely picked up &#8211; including here on the Weinberg blog. I thought it would make sense to bring you some more detail of his thinking. To do so, I&#8217;ve reached back to April 2010, when Gates delivered a convincing pro-nuclear presentation at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology that conveys the same message as his Colorado remarks (MIT is the same university, incidentally, which is home to President Obama&#8217;s pro-nuclear nominee for Energy Secretary, physicist Ernest Moniz). In his MIT speech, presented about a year before the nuclear meltdowns at Fukushima, Gates advocates not simply for nuclear, but for new, alternative nuclear technologies, such as the breeder reactor under development at the company that the Microsoft billionaire... <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/11/bill-gates-excellent-case-for-new-types-of-nuclear-power/">[read more]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4 style="text-align: center"><em>&#8220;Nuclear innovation stopped in the 1970s.&#8221;</em></h4>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe width="500" height="281" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/dbbq_KdPzjE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Bill Gates has been making nuclear headlines over the last few days after the told a gathering of international energy executives near Denver that solar and wind technologies won&#8217;t cut it as a source of baseload power, and that the U.S. government should fund nuclear research and development.</p>
<p>His remarks were reported by Reuters and have been widely picked up &#8211; <a href="http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/08/good-week-for-nuclear-environmental-economic-backing-from-japan-bill-gates-mit-and-obama/">including here on the Weinberg blog</a>.</p>
<p>I thought it would make sense to bring you some more detail of his thinking. To do so, I&#8217;ve reached back to April 2010, when Gates delivered a convincing pro-nuclear presentation at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology that conveys the same message as his Colorado remarks (MIT is the same university, incidentally, which is home to President Obama&#8217;s pro-nuclear nominee for Energy Secretary, physicist Ernest Moniz).</p>
<p>In his MIT speech, presented about a year before the nuclear meltdowns at Fukushima, Gates advocates not simply for nuclear, but for new, alternative nuclear technologies, such as the breeder reactor under development at the company that the Microsoft billionaire co-founded, called TerraPower. He even gives some lips service to molten salt reactors, even if he doesn&#8217;t seem enamored of them.</p>
<p>&#8220;Nuclear is one of the directions that we should innovate in,&#8221; he says, a little less than four minutes into the clip. &#8220;Nuclear innovation stopped in the 1970s. We basically have this sub (submarine) designed thing that was put into Shippingport (Shippingport, Pa.) for the first power generator and we basically built 400 of those that are all kind of custom but not in any interesting way. They&#8217;re all LWRs (light water reactors)  and PWRs (pressurized water reactors) and the industry did not innovate much at all. There&#8217;s this third generation passive safety AP 1000, but except for that they didn&#8217;t do much.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>CUTE SOLAR</strong></p>
<p>Gates points out that the energy per atom from nuclear fuel &#8220;is about a million times better than coal or natural gas.&#8221; But without the development of new types of nuclear power, the industry will struggle to take advantage of that in an economically competitive fashion, he notes.</p>
<p>Reactors like TerraPower&#8217;s and like molten salt reactors can burn fuel more efficiently and safely than do conventional reactors, can use nuclear waste as fuel, and leave less waste.</p>
<p>I encourage you to watch the entire video &#8211; it&#8217;s less than eight minutes &#8211; to hear Gates&#8217; analysis of solar and wind which he calls &#8220;cute up to a point,&#8221; of the material science problems associated with the &#8220;damn neutrons&#8221; in his own reactor, and the  even greater materials challenges facing fusion developers.</p>
<p>&#8220;If you look at the fusion guys, their neutrons are like a thousand times worse than our neutrons,&#8221; says Gates. &#8220;Those guys have 14 MeV neutrons &#8211; good luck to them.&#8221;</p>
<p>As a popular New York sportscaster used to say, let&#8217;s go to the video. It was posted by the Washington, D.C.-based  Nuclear Energy Institute, which calls it &#8220;I Love Nuclear&#8221; (words Gates actually uses). Click anywhere on the image of Gates above to start watching.</p>
<p><em>Video from NEINetwork via YouTube. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.the-weinberg-foundation.org/2013/03/11/bill-gates-excellent-case-for-new-types-of-nuclear-power/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
